Guide to the Don Barr papers,1975-2003.
Barr, Donald Papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Don Barr papers, 1975-2003.
23-24-3670
Donald Barr
2 cubic feet.
Publications, Reports, Correspondence, Printed Materials
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes course material, publications, correspondence, and seminar material pertaining to Barr's career in the College of Human Ecology and his work on multicultural education and social injustices.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Professor emeritus of Policy Analysis and Management, formerly the Dept. of Human Service Studies, Cornell University
Don Barr was born May 7, 1935 in Geneva, Ohio. He earned a B.S. (1957) in social and earth sciences at Miami University in Ohio, an M.A. (1959) in sociology and a Ph.D. (1964) in guidance and counseling, both at Indiana University. When Barr first came to Cornell in 1971, he was the director of the college's office of counseling and admissions. Later, he moved to the Department of Human Service Studies (HSS), now called Policy Analysis and Management (PAM) and served a term as chair of this department.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes course material, publications, correspondence, and seminar material pertaining to Barr's career in the College of Human Ecology and his work on multicultural education and social injustices.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Barr, Donald; Barr, Donald.; Cornell University--Faculty; New York State College of Human Ecology.Dept. of Human Service Studies.; New York State College of Human Ecology.Dept. of Policy Analysis and Management.
Subjects:
College students--Political activity.; Multicultural education--United States.; Race identity.; Race relations--United States.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Biographical
Series II. Publications
Series III. Correspondence
Series IV. Lectures, Seminars, Workshops, Presentations and Proposals
Series V. Course Material
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Biographical
- Vita and Biographical Material, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Annual Reports, 1971-2000 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Awards (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Department Curriculum Committee, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series II. Publications
- The Society for Applied Anthropology, Annual Meeting, Toronto, 1984-03 (Box 1)
- Counselor Education And Supervision Volume 11 No.1, 1971-09 (Box 1)
- International Society of Political Psychology, Official Program Directory, 1984-06 (Box 1)
- Catalyst, A Socialist Journal of the Social Services, 1984 (Box 1)
- NASPA Journal Volume 26 No. 2, 1988 (Box 1)
  Winter
- The Personnel And Guidance Journal Volume 46 No.6, 1968-02 (Box 1)
- Community Mental Health Journal Volume 10 No. 2, 1974 (Box 1)
  Summer
- Athena, Cornell Women's Center, 1997 (Box 1)
  Fall
- Teacher Corps, Team Leaders Handbook, 1977 (Box 1)
- The Bulletin of the Association of College Unions - International Volume 55 No.3, 1987-05 (Box 1)
- "Humanist Images of Man", Association of Humanistic Psychology, Eighth Annual Meeting, 1970 (Box 1)
- Family Support: Framework for the Future, 1992-05 (Box 1)
- Program Ideas and Research in Nutrition Education Abstracts, Society for Nutrition Education, Tenth Annual Meeting, Washington DC, 1977-07 (Box 1)
- "Sharing Educational Success", Sixth Annual Report, National Advisory Council on Supplementary Centers and Services, 1974-03 (Box 1)
- "Power to the Family!", Human Ecology Forum, Volume 14 No. 1 (Box 1)
- African Studies and Research Center, Cornell University Newsletter Volume 2. No. 1, 1990 (Box 1)
  Spring
- New York FarmNet, An Information and Referral System for Farm Families in New York State (Box 1)
- Publications (Box 1, Folder 5)
- An Introduction on Henry Thoreau's Resistance to Civil Government (Box 1, Folder 6)
- A Retrospective Study of the Impact of Race and Class on Academic Success at Ithaca High School (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Critical Reflections of Power in the Empowerment Process, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series III. Correspondence
- Articles (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Memo to Board of Trustees on the Status of Minority Students at Cornell, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- With Various Deans in the College of Human Ecology, 1970-2002 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Articles, 1976-1986 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Articles, 1987-1990 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Articles, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Articles, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Articles, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Articles, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Articles, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Articles, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Articles, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Series IV. Lectures, Seminars, Workshops, Presentations and Proposals
- Institutional Change (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Cultural Differences (Bennet), Personal Journey Differences (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Cornell Empowerment Project (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Social Ecological Model, Feedback in the Empowerment Process, Planned Changes (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Affirmative Action - Reports (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Lectures - Various Topics, 1980-1999 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Lecture - Anti-Racism, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Lecture - Privilege (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Lecture - James - Social Stratification (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Lecture -Theories, Racism, Colonization (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Lecture -Ringer Duality (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Lecture -American Indian (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Lecture - Slavery Reconstruction - Jim Crow Period (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Lecture - Education - Racism and Social Action (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Lecture - Anti-Social Control (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Lecture - White Country Club (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Lecture - Old and New Paradigms (Box 1, Folder 37)
- School Rules - BJM (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Lecture - Hate Materials, 1990-1999 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Lecture - Civil Rights, 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Lecture - Ethnic Myth - Steinberg's Notes (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Lecture - White Supremacy - Hook and Macintosh Articles (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Lecture - Institutional Reason (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Lecture - Jewish Immigrants from Ethnic Myth (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Lecture - Racism Stats (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Lecture - Scientific Racism (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Lecture - Racism and Human Services (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Lecture - Social Class (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Lecture - Racism and Oppression (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Lecture - Apartheid (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Apartheid/ Divestment - Faculty and Staff Response, 1978-1985 (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Apartheid Issues - Memos, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Ithaca City Council Statement, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Divestment - Memos/ Articles, 1985-1989 (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Articles -Divestment, 1989-1995 (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Alternative Community School (Box 1, Folder 55)
- Workshop- Southern Illinois University at Carbondale, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 56)
- Proposal -"High School for the Study of Human Services", 1984 (Box 1, Folder 57)
- Proposal - Rural New York Farmworker Opportunities, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Presentation - Sue Watkin's Class, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Proposal - "Power and Empowerment" and Final Report to the Ford Foundation, 1986-1987, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Workshop - Keuka College, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Proposal - Empowerment - Dominican Sisters, Ohio, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Workshop - Youth Bureau, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Workshop - Rider College, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Workshop - Youth Development, Youth Bureau, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Proposal - Funding for Training for Trainers - Migrant Workers, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Meeting - National Treasury Employees Union, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Conference - Community and Leadership Development, Texas, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Ithaca School Board, 1989,1991 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Workshop - Fall Creek School, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Panel Discussion - Ithaca College, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Workshop - University of Wyoming, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Workshop - Elmira College, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Workshop -Minneapolis, Minnesota, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Proposal - College of Forestry, Syracuse, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Seminar - Coastal Bend Family Summit, Texas, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Conference - "Partners in Policymaking", 1994 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Workshop - Tioga Central Schools, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Workshop - Spencer Van Ellen Schools, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Workshop - Cortland State, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Meeting - Ithaca City School District Administration, Parents, Students of Color, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Training - Ithaca City School District Orientation for Staff, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Workshop - Diversity - Steuben County, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Conference - Migrant Program Education, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Review - Family Resources Coalition, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Community Empowerment Project GIAC, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Workshop - International Early Childhood Care and Development Summer Institute, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Leadership Seminar - Ithaca City School District - "Elimination of Prejudice/Institutional Racism", 1995 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Leadership Institute - NYC Principals, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Workshop - Cortland State, 1995-02 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Workshop - GIAC Staff, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Lecture -"Breaking The Code of Silence About Racial Tension In Rural America: An Applied Research Project", 1996-01 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Workshop - Ithaca City School District Bus Drivers, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Leadership Seminar - Fayette County Public Schools, Kentucky, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Lecture - Community Nutrition Seminar, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Training - Tompkins County Human Rights Commission, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- City of Ithaca Affirmative Action Committee Discussion Ideas, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- "Children First" - Survey on Anti-Racism - Akwesasne Mohawk School, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 41)
- Debate - Multicultural Education, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Workshop - Ithaca City School District - Physical Education Teachers, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Community Youth Empowerment Project, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 44)
- Workshop - Partners in Policymaking - Arc of Nebraska, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 45)
- Ithaca High School - Affirmative Action, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 46)
- Leadership Institute - Ithaca City School District, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 47)
- Leadership Seminar - New York City - "Case Study on Racism", 1997 (Box 2, Folder 48)
- Leadership Seminar - Schenectady School District, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 49)
- Workshop - Building Partners in Policymaking, Nebraska, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 50)
- Meeting - Enfield School, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 51)
- Race and Education - Ithaca High School, 1998-11 (Box 2, Folder 52)
- Leadership Seminar - Geneva Presbytery Pastors, 1998-09-1999-05 (Box 2, Folder 53)
- African Institute Presentation, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 54)
- Series V. Course Materials
- Handouts (Box 2, Folder 55)
- Three Dimensions of Power, Empowerment/Power, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 56)
- HSS 101 - Models of Human Service (Box 2, Folder 57)
- HSS 101, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 58)
- HSS 101 - Steps in Problem Solving, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 59)
- HSS 101/PAM 180, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 60)
- HD 280 "Racism in American Society" (Box 2, Folder 61)
- HSS 280, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 62)
- PAM 240, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 63)
- PAM 280 - Readings Book I, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 64)
- PAM 280 - Readings Book II, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 65)
- PAM 280, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 66)
- PAM 280 "Race, Power and Privilege in the US", 2003 (Box 2, Folder 67)
- PAM 280 Syllabus, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 68)
- PAM 402, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 69)
- PAM 471, 1999-05-2000-09 (Box 2, Folder 70)